Guide to the William Silver Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Silver papers
1947-2007
MS 1897
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.25
14 boxes
986
The papers document William Silver's personal life, seminary thesis, his application for ordination into the United Presbyterian Church, and his later life in the Cherry Grove community on Fire Island, New York. Particularly well documented is Silver's coming out process and the Presbyterian Church's debate on the ordination of homosexuals in the 1970s. The papers consist of journals, writings, sermons, correspondence, photographs, newsletters, news clippings, and printed material.
Silver, William, 1947-2007
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Estate of William Silver, 2007, 2008, and 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The papers include images in digital formats. Further description of file formats provided in Collection Contents.
Biographical / Historical
William Silver, who was also known as Violet, was born September 8, 1947, in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. He received a Bachelor of Arts (1969) from Ohio Wesleyan University, majoring in Fine Arts and Pre-theology. He received a Masters of Divinity from the Union Theological Seminary in 1973. In his final year at Seminary, Silver came out as a gay man and based his thesis project on his coming out process, or "experience of liberation." The project consisted of a series of paintings and a journal where he documented his coming out process.
In 1975 Silver requested ordination in the Presbytery of New York. His request sparked a two year, church-wide debate on the ordination of gay men in the Presbyterian Church. The General Assembly of United Presbyterian Church in the United States adopted a policy that barred self-affirming, practicing gay men from ordination in 1978. The policy, while blocking ordination, allowed for accepting homosexuals into the church and even ordaining repentant homosexuals who led a celibate or heterosexual life-style. Additionally, the policy protected gay men who were ordained prior to 1978 from being removed from the ministry. Silver continued his involvement with the church as a layman until the 1980s.
He worked as a graphic artist and events organizer. He was a long-time resident and active member of the Cherry Grove, Fire Island (New York) community. He was known for his "High Purple Tea" events and as the publisher of the monthly "Violet's Wild Cherry" events guide. Silver died of complications due to AIDS in 2007.
Scope and Contents
The papers document William Silver's personal life, seminary thesis, his application for ordination into the United Presbyterian Church, and his later life in the Cherry Grove community on Fire Island, New York. Particularly well documented is Silver's coming out process and the Presbyterian Church's debate on the ordination of homosexuals in the 1970s. The papers consist of journals, writings, sermons, correspondence, photographs, newsletters, news clippings, and printed material.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by accession.
Gay community -- New York (State) -- Fire Island (Island); Gay men; Homosexuality -- Religious aspects -- Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.); Ordination of gays -- Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.); Cherry Grove (N.Y.); Fire Island (N.Y.: Island); LGBTQ resource; Silver, William, 1947-2007; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A
- Inventory, 1972-2007
  - Biographical
    - Resume and biographical sketch, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Memorial service, print materials and photographs, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Digital photographs, 2007; 23 computer files (JPEG)
        General note
        Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
  - Seminary thesis and request for ordination
    - Thesis, "Liberation Becoming Free"
      - Journal, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Exhibition (Newspaper clipping and promotional materials), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Central Presbyterian Church and the Central Arts Ministry, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gay Caucus Synod of the Northeast, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Presbyterian Gay Caucus/Presbyterians for Gay Concerns, 1974-1978
      - General, circa 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Newsletter, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Presbytery News (Presbytery of New York City), 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - United Presbyterian Church in the United States of America
      - General Assembly
        - Assembly meeting, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - General Assembly Daily News, 1976, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - News clippings and articles on the ordination of homosexuals, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Permanent Judicial Commission, decision of, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Task Force on Homosexuality, [1978] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Writings and sermons, circa 1972-1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978 and undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cherry Grove, Fire Island
    - Cherry Grove Garden Club, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Community service awards, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - High Purple Tea, posters and invitation, 1992-2003 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - News clippings from Fire Island News and Fire Island Tide, 1995-2005 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Photographs
      - Silver, William, 1998-2003 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Friends and events, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
      - Digital photographs, mostly for "Violet's Wild Cherry" events guide, circa 2000-2007
        Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
        Formats include: 7 Adobe Photoshop files, 30 Binary Interchange File Format (BIFF) Workbook files, 9 Encapsulated PostScript File Format files, 212 Exchangeable Image File Format files, 4 IBM DisplayWrite Document files, 122 JPEG File Interchange Format files, 2 Text files, 29 Quark Xpress Data files, 80 Tagged Image File Format files, 66 Windows Bitmap files, 1 Windows Executable file, 1 Zip Format file.
    - "Violet's Wild Cherry," events guide, 1996-2007 (Box 3, Folder 26-28)
    - Miscellaneous, 1995-2007 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Digital files, 2002-2007 (Box 4)
- Additional Material, 1947-2006; Accession 2011-M-060
  Arrangement
  The addition is arranged chronologically within four sections: Personal Writings and Memorabilia, Presbyterian Files, Photographs and Drawings.
  Scope and Contents
  The addition to the William Silver papers consists of photographs, slides and negatives; Gay Presbyterian-related materials; personal and business correspondence; drawings, childhood and academic materials; and materials related to Fire Island events.
  - Personal writings and memorabilia
    - Diaries and correspondence
      - Correspondence to parents with notes and diary, 1965-1968, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      - Postcards, Circa 1970s, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Personal calendars, 1973, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        General
        Includes some business correspondence.
      - Diary, 1980-1989, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Greeting cards and event invitations, 1984-1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ephemera and memorabilia
      - School and personal memorabilia, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Includes baby book, baptismal certificate, 4-H Club material, high school diploma, and graduation invitation and program.
      - School memorabilia, Circa 1952-1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Includes report cards, PSAT and SAT scores, junior class play script and program, and scholarship certificates.
      - Scrapbook, Circa 1957 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Boy Scouts of America ephemera and memorabilia, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Includes postcards, brochure, menu, badges and book mark from Philmont Scout Ranch, Cimarron, NM.
      - Ohio Wesleyan University event ephemera (mainly flyers), 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Collegiate records and memorabilia, 1965-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
        Contains scholarship award certificates (including Phi Beta Kappa), Union Theological Seminary transcript, and undergraduate and graduate student identification, grade cards, commencement programs and diplomas.
      - "Field Work and Social Welfare," class report, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Personal memorabilia, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Items include business cards, employee identification, and Montour wooden rings.
      - Pennsylvania State University College of Argriculture, "4-H Club Games", Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Collected writings, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Presbyterian files
    - Sermons and writings, Circa 1970-2006 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
    - Publications and ephemera
      - General
        - Central Arts News, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Presbytery News, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Central Arts Ministry budget and church mission statement, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Village Presbyterian Fellowship ephemera and church documents, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - The Presbyterian Layman, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - 190th General Assemby of the United Presbyterian Church in the United States of America (U.P.C.) policy statements, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        - Judson Memorial Church parishioner memorabilia, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Presbyterian churches brochure and service programs, 1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
        - General Assembly Daily News, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Frying Pan, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - Hymnals and sheet music, 1979-1980s (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Gay and lesbian
        - Articles on homosexuality, 1975-1981, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
        - Presbyterians for Lesbian/Gay Concerns, Presbyterian Gay Caucus: budgets, reports, and membership ephemera, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - U.P.C. reports on the church and homosexuality, 1978, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Presbyterian publications on homosexuality, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - National March for Lesbian and Gay Rights event ephemera, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - More Light, 1979-1980, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Presbyterians for Lesbian and Gay Concerns event ephemera, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        - Professional Church Leadership (P.C.L.) Committee Task Force reports, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - Gay and Lesbian Pride Guide, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - Central Arts Gallery events ephemera, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - Creative Ministry in an Age of Ambiguity ephemera, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - Ordination request, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Photographs
    - Prints
      - Family and friends, Circa 1950-circa 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
      - Boy Scouts of America, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - High school classmates, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Family photographs, Pittsburgh, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - William Silver art, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Travel photographs: Oregon, Washington, and British Columbia, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - William Silver photography
        Includes prints and contact prints.
        - "Architecture", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 8)
        - "People in Motion", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
        - "Martin Luther King", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 10)
        - "Night Plus", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
        - "Laundromat, Indoor", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - William Silver -- Ohio Wesleyan University, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Family and friends, 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Union Theological Seminary, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - World Trade Center, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Family and friends, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Architectural Digest events, 1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Family and friends, 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Christmas parties, 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Miss Cherry Pageant, 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
      - Cherry Grove, printout of photographs, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Cherry Grove, New York, 1994 summer (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
      - "Invasion of the Pines", 1996 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
      - Cherry Hills, 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
      - Miss Cherry Pageant, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - "Cherry Grove with Bill's new apartment: Violet's Gate" and Miss Cherry Pageant, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
      - Captioned photographs, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
      - Chelsea Garden Club Gay Pride events, Undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Cherry Hills charity events and Violet's Purple Party, Undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Events, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
      - Friends and pets, Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Presbyterians for Lesbian and Gay Concerns Pride March, Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Rawhide and Rawhidettes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - William Silver personal portraits, Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - William Silver roof garden, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
      - "Violet's Purple Party", Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Untitled photo album, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
      - Untitled prints and contact prints, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
    - Slides
      - Personal slides, 1975-1981, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Negatives
      - "Abbey", Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - "Architecture and Conference", Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - "Arts Board: Mozelle/Bill Silver et al. -- group for christmas card", Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - "Christmas", Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - "Designs - Nature and Man", Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - "Laundry", Undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - "Martin Luther King", Undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - "Mother and Arch", Undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - "Night Shots", Undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - "People in Action", Undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - "Senior Show", undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - "Spring", Undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
      - "Upward Bound", Undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
      - Unidentified, Undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Drawings
    - Crayon drawings, card designs, pen sketches, 1979, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Sketchpad with watercolor, charcoal, ink, and pencil drawings, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Anatomical ink drawings and sketchpad with crayon drawings, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Pencil sketches and crayon drawings, 1970, 1975, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)